[SPEAKER_03]: So, I thought of talking about the, well, in relation to the previous talks and the mind and the wild animal series, the first three fetters and the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: How does it relate to it?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I guess we can
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's take Sīlabhata Paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be Sīlabhata Paramāsa from your point of view, in terms of the citta, the wild animal that's there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it a fetter?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or rather, describe the fetter.
[SPEAKER_03]: In this context, the simile we've been using lots of times... Is Daniel affected?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You are not seeing
[SPEAKER_02]: The extent to which it's being agitated...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't mean generally, it's the animal factor.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, specifically, it's the animal factor by syllabus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not seeing the... it being agitated by you doing some practice, acting out of a sense of duty or a sense of doing virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: But wouldn't that be... wouldn't it be right to say that you're affected?
[SPEAKER_03]: You're the fettered one, because you're the one obsessing over and not seeing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, which one is it then?
[SPEAKER_03]: The animal or you?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd say it would be closer to say you, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, what I was thinking... to say it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Was that, eh... it would be kind of akin to, in terms of the simile, sort of just having a... like, you know, okay, in theory, I need to tame this animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... but you don't see the animal.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know how to relate to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have any... and so you just have... and all you can do is have some kind of... you try this, like some kind of set of instruction, and now if I follow these things, I hope that it will calm the animal down, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, see, at that stage, why are you not seeing the animal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Precisely because of expecting the result of peace or something to come out of following some kind of prescribed thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, your thought of what the animal is, is like going to be on the other end of when I finish doing all of these motions.
[SPEAKER_03]: And who are you doing those motions for then?
[SPEAKER_03]: If the animal is not seen, who are you doing the...
[SPEAKER_03]: The duty and the precepts for?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: For yourself, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the animal is not seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not even paying attention to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, you're doing it out of your craving, your pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Animal is second.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want to first satisfy this discomfort.
[SPEAKER_03]: Of course, animal is related to that internally, but
[SPEAKER_03]: You are basically running past it and doing all these things just to appease yourself, your own craving, your own insecurity, your own doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why the animal is not even seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intentionally, just, no, no, this is more important for me.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why people would struggle to give up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sīlabhātparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not, oh, thank you, wow, it's just like a
[SPEAKER_03]: Intellectual mistake.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's you doing it, because you're obviously doing it for yourself, in the sense of you're finding some sense of safety, some sense of clarity, some sense of method, that I can adhere to, without having to endure the ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything else is second.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the message you're conveying to the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: That, well, you are unimportant.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's where it's your burden.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where it's your fetter.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're the fetter one.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the whole point of, you know, we've been saying so many times, that you have to kind of go against yourself and your own sort of
[SPEAKER_03]: A degree of your own inclinations, like you take on the pieces, but then you you want to overly define them.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, well, no, actually now that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: That will make things worse.
[SPEAKER_03]: Needing to overly define, to specify, to avoid doubt arising, to clarify, to rehash millions of times.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, but the tradition, the way, the duty, the agenda, the teacher said this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yes, you need to learn what the rules are.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to learn what the extent of virtue to be developed is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, once you do that, then, basically, now you actually need to start catching your own... your own self, when you're trying to overdo it, overly define it, just to get the extra sense of safety, because more is better.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: More is tighter.
[SPEAKER_03]: And tighter is not better.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like in that Q&A in Poland we did, when I was asking people, like, would you eat at 12.15, if you didn't eat the meal?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, what's the problem?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would you stop at 12.00?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's not the rule.
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha never said that.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said, stop by noon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Noon, well, when it's the highest, which means it's always going to be a matter of guess, of a guess.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the problem with that is, if I don't decide at 12.00, and I just use that general sense of, is it the noon now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Close.
[SPEAKER_03]: Should I eat?
[SPEAKER_03]: Should I not?
[SPEAKER_03]: You start second-guessing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You start checking your reasons.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would you eat?
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you... Am I really hungry?
[SPEAKER_03]: All these things will be now revolving and you will have to deal with them.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will have to bear them, deal with them, make a decision and then live with the decision.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of that, it's actually closer now to talking to your mind rightly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, if you were to just... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Twelve zero zero.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the time of purity.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: I can eat at 11.55 like a pig, shove things down my throat, not think about why I eat, how much I eat, do I need to eat all of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I don't need to, because as long as I stop before 12.00, I am pure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Factually, I am blameless, because I did not cross second past the noon.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you see how ridiculous that view is.
[SPEAKER_03]: And people won't give it up, because it offers clarity and safety, and almost righteousness, sense of righteousness as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just because the animal is not... it's almost like you just sort of, I don't know, put it away in a cage, so that you don't get to see it, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you don't have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the whole... see how that reinforces then the view that the purity comes out of these random observances.
[SPEAKER_03]: 11.55 is pure, 12.00 it's not pure.
[SPEAKER_03]: 12.05?
[SPEAKER_03]: Poof!
[SPEAKER_03]: You might as well disrobe and go and get married.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, like, there is no virtue for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it becomes very irrational and... and fettering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's not going to be just a... as I said, a simple question of correcting the misinformation for that person to... or drop it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're going to have... now I have to feel
[SPEAKER_03]: The weight of that insecurity that they've been running away from, by jumping into these overly defined observances, basically, they're not even rules.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just for the sake of avoiding ambiguity, doubt, second-guessing, reflection, all things that pertain to the mind, to the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you allow those things to come, then, basically, you start keeping the precepts for the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: For the revelation, clarification, containment of the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you're unburdened, completely.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not fettered anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to do anything for yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't have to do anything, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just abstaining from doing these things and animals closer and closer and clearer and clearer.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I guess you can see how that relates to the factor of doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: When doubt is present, what would that person do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it'd be the same kind of procedure in terms of, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me find an answer to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me kind of clarify it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me, just for the sake of... And it's exactly the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you keep yourself within that principle by expecting the peace or the kind of resolution to come from me getting the answer to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: From the letter of the text, from the external.
[SPEAKER_00]: From some external something, anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, you would be, again, looking past the animal intentionally.
[SPEAKER_03]: To basically, as I said, appease your own craving and insecurity and not even want to deal with with the doubt, because it's too pressuring.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's like, it's kind of funny.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, somebody would be doing all of these things and actually kind of feeling
[SPEAKER_00]: But I feel, you see, there's no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I do all these things and then I'm kind of at peace and, you know, I have all my ways of dealing with things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start, like, not doing them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like you've taken, like, ten steps backwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because, actually, you only just started.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you become very dependent on those circumstances, on those highly managed circumstances.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, there are monks that disrobe
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they've forsaken the entire training, because they ended up in the environment where nobody would offer the food properly, you know, traditionally.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's like, you realize, like, wow, how deluded you would have been all the time, to not even realize important as important and unimportant as unimportant, to not be able to distinguish.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in their eyes, it was better to forsake the entire practice for freeing yourself from saṃsāra, than to
[SPEAKER_03]: But you won't go to hell, you know, committing to sensuality and basically following your senses like an animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that will not take you to hell at all.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's easier.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you still don't take on responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, even when they disrobe, they wouldn't have taken on responsibility for doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It would have been, well, because you know the purity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, okay, okay, fine, fair enough, fair enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, I just did it because of this, and this was done because of this, and this was done because of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, please don't put any of that weight on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not having to have the burden of making a choice and really feeling like what I'm going to do is going to bear consequences.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how does it relate to Atavāda then?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're not seeing the mind in these two examples of thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: You're intentionally going past it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you intentionally refuse to basically look in its direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: You do not want to take your eyes from the external sense of duty,
[SPEAKER_03]: Sense of methods, sense of performances, sense of blind adherence to the virtue and, as I said, the sense of duty that defines you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And same to that external sense of... external things that you'll be seeking to appease your own doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, because, see, the resolution comes from outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: When I get the right information, then doubt cannot arise anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Until it does, in which case I need to update my information, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why is Atharvāda the third factor with those two?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, why does looking past the animal, in the sense we just described, why does that
[SPEAKER_03]: Cause, I suppose, would likely be a good word.
[SPEAKER_03]: Athavāda.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that the cause of Athavāda?
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm trying to give you an answer, but look at the space in between.
[SPEAKER_03]: Remember how you used to look past it?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is that cause?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so what is Athavāda?
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's translated as belief in self.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's obviously a bit sadder than just believing in yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the main defining characteristic of Atavāda?
[SPEAKER_00]: External.
[SPEAKER_03]: External.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it all has in common.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, by depending on an external, like, duty, authority...
[SPEAKER_00]: The weight is at the external.
[SPEAKER_00]: The assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a complete assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like the external resolution to the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: External resolution to the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: External...
[SPEAKER_03]: Methods independent of me, my intention, my effort, my reflection, my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is how you keep your sense of self independent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but before that, before you even took on these duties and tried to practice, again, sense objects, dependence on sense objects, desire, delight in sense objects, being defined by possessions, everything external, external, external, external.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, your sense of self exists now on account of the assumption of that external, I, independent of me, independent of my experience as a whole, independent of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're reinforcing that assumption.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you were reinforcing that assumption through non-virtue, non-restraint sensuality, but now you are not removing that assumption either, because of... your practice is the practice of sīlabhātu paramāsa and avoiding of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're still very much reinforcing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sādhāvāda goes hand in hand with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you say, actually, in a way, I mean, that's why it's like, I don't know which sutta it says, but it's like, you know, a baby doesn't think about duty or about doubt or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the same sense, like somebody who's just
[SPEAKER_00]: Normal sensuality, not practicing, doesn't necessarily mean, you know, it wouldn't kind of come up this, you know, but it's like this tendency that can only... it is, it is there, it's underlying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you were to try to go against the sensuality and wake up, that's the first thing you're going to encounter.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's... you're going to see what was fettering you, which is going to be that dependence on that, as I said, external definition for what the truth is, in a sense of
[SPEAKER_03]: To alleviate the doubt, information and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: The external weight of the authority, of tradition, dhamma, suttas, doesn't matter, but I'll adhere to this as a method, as a prescribed steps, virtue and duty, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: And same, I'm keeping the virtue for the same, out of the same attitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm virtuous because that will somehow magically in return do this work for me on the inside that I'm very much intentionally refusing to look at.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, say then, somebody's becoming aware of this and then they have doubt, pressure in their mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't just automatically go out and seek the resolution.
[SPEAKER_03]: They endure it.
[SPEAKER_03]: They don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: They learn to come within that, not at the expense of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same in terms of the
[SPEAKER_03]: That sense of duty and virtue, they still keep it, obviously.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't go against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, you don't... well, you take responsibility for doing so.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you start shifting that emphasis on, like, no, no, no, it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: Things are unwholesome because they're rooted in unwholesome intentions, and things are wholesome because they're rooted in wholesome intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's something that needs to be repeated, reflected upon, and drilled into you, so that you stop automatically just falling onto the assumption of the external duty, resolution, authority, method, weight, removal, safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, say a person now, they induce the doubt rightly, takes on weight of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're not just doing it blindly,
[SPEAKER_03]: To appease their own ideal and desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, exactly, the signs of the mind would be more and more apparent, the space in between, as a real entity, as a real phenomenon, as something that you're just completely looking past, looking through.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say it that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: How does that then free you from those fetters?
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, we said why it would free you from the factor of duty, because you're not doing it, as I said, out of that ideal that inherently wants avoidance of responsibility and wants things to come externally on account of me just going through the motions, do what I'm told, don't be left alone, think for myself, that's too much.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, obviously, once you start seeing the mind, you realize that, no, this is supposed to be outlining this, it has nothing to do with me.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're relieved of the duty.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're relieved of that entire burden.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're unfettered.
[SPEAKER_03]: Doubt?
[SPEAKER_03]: How would it relieve you of the burden and the factor of doubt, seeing your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: It relieves you of the burden of having to do anything on account of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you never had to do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't see that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that was your factor of duty.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, now you don't have to do anything, that's your factor of duty gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: But now the factor of doubt, you might not be doing anything on account of it, but it's still there unpleasant, fettering you.
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you be unfettered?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or rather, how does seeing your mind, seeing the wild animal, how does that unfetter you from the burden of the doubt?
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't doubt anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, when we're describing the, like, the deactivation of... of what?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is being deactivated?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, there are only two options.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, which one is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: It is citta.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: When the animal calms down within the doubt, you realize that's what the doubt was.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was not the uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was the agitation of the animal that you were fueling through constantly seeking the resolution externally and not allowing the containment.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you calm the animal within the doubt a sufficient amount of times,
[SPEAKER_03]: That doubt part of the uncertainty, the pressure, the pain, is gone completely, because it was solely because of the agitated animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you realize, oh, yeah, I still have uncertainty, but there is no more doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And certainly, then, there is no more view now that it will come to resolution of the of the external kind of information and permutation and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, obviously, you can't just deactivate it at that stage and tell it to calm down.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to confine it within the doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that becomes your mode of being.
[SPEAKER_03]: Until the animal calms down within it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you see what's left.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you see what was gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's not... that goes hand-in-hand with that safety as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: That you would be
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the first three factors go away together.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not first, and then second, and then... What I was thinking, it's kind of really more or less...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: The three implications of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: The safety you find in the external sense of duty, definition, authority, methods.
[SPEAKER_03]: The safety that then shelters you from doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when doubt comes, you basically fight the doubt by clarifying your external safety even more.
[SPEAKER_03]: And all of that just reinforces your assumption of the external as where the sense of yourself is, independent of your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you don't think myself is external, simply depending on the assumption of that degree of external, that is what yourself is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in order for the mind to calm down within that, yeah, well, you have to confine it within that and not act out of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there's that...
[SPEAKER_03]: I think there's like a Zen... Well, it wasn't a koan, it was a saying or something, when... when, like, when he start...
[SPEAKER_03]: He says, before the practice...
[SPEAKER_03]: This monk wrote that.
[SPEAKER_03]: He says, before the practice, mountains were mountains, forests were forests, rivers were rivers, something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: When he started practicing, mountains were not mountains, and forests were not forests, and rivers were not rivers.
[SPEAKER_03]: He is, like, just...
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything, top to bottom, was infected, affected by that doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, after his mind calmed down, the forests were forests, mountains were mountains, rivers were rivers.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you had to go through that withdrawal, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So now, let's say, the animal has been sufficiently tamed, so the first... the fuel
[SPEAKER_03]: For the first three fetters, it has become redundant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, you're incapable of healing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're incapable of finding safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no need for safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all of your previous efforts would be meaningless now.
[SPEAKER_03]: You couldn't even conceive to assume again what you've kind of unassumed, what you've seen through.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how would then... what would then be...
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, in relation to the animal, the removal of the other two course of factors, centrality and the will.
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you describe that, from the point of view of the citta?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'd say, just to compare it with what you just described in terms of doubt, like you would be within the feather of doubt, you would be doubting,
[SPEAKER_00]: With uncertainty, for as long as you kind of immediately jump onto, as soon as there's uncertainty, I must, I must resolve it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the uncertainty becomes doubt when you kind of go and resolve it with something external.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you fail to see that the whole kind of pressure of of the uncertainty that makes it into doubt is the animal that is like agitated, agitated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you kind of realize, wait, no, that that is the problem, the animal calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes impossible to do the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say, in terms of sensuality or ill-will, it would be the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you would be having the fetter, or the sensuality is there, for as long as, like the, let's say, prospect of pleasure from sight, sound, smell, taste, touch is,
[SPEAKER_00]: That implies the resolution of that pressure through going and getting those sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you... And what is like the truth in that case, is that the the pressure or the burden, the reason that it's pressuring the prospect of sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, is again the agitated animal that is like
[SPEAKER_00]: Delighting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and if the animal were to calm down sufficiently, like, thoroughly... See, the animal can calm down, but that doesn't necessarily immediately free you from the fetters.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not... this is my question to myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to really, kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, well, let's start like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, as when I was saying about the
[SPEAKER_03]: When I was asking, who do you do it for?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it you or the animal?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the same question then comes to centrality in your will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you still on the level of wanting it yourself?
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you still on the level of hating it yourself?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or... No, you don't really want it, but you can't help the pressure towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't really hate, but I can't help but be pressured by the thoughts towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if it's the second one?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the second one would be if you would have undone the first one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, first you need to, yourself, stop wanting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, no, I generally don't want this.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I can't help it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Of course, you're helping it in terms of not acting out of it, but I can't help but have the desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when you can start to differentiate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aha, okay, so it's... that's the animal's desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the animal's preference.
[SPEAKER_03]: And yes, for as long as that animal still will have even possibility of such desires, I'm liable to act out, even if I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you were doing it for yourself by not seeing where the problem was, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you can make that distinction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, those suttas, when the Buddha says, like, oh, yes, I saw how little satisfaction, how perilous sensuality is, how much better renunciation is, but my mind didn't want to leap towards renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It still wanted sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, I did everything right.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have not... No, it's not that I was not seeing the peril, but the mind was still wanting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was not accepting the the terms of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, oh, why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, well, because I haven't made it clear to it, basically, the gratification danger in scale.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to now start what we spoke in previous talks.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can have the calm mind, but if it still prefers sensuality as the means of pleasure, the animal, you're still liable to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to calm it, but not for its own sake, but only for the sake to be able to start talking to it, and conveying that it should not want it either.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's better for it to not want it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And same with your will.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that the principle of
[SPEAKER_03]: We're drawing from a degree of the assumed... extent of the assumed external, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just obviously on a subtle level, but... you need to stop acting externally, thinking towards external, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, as the cause and the reason of your sensuality, as the cause and the reason of your real will.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you don't,
[SPEAKER_03]: You're just doing it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not even seeing the mind in relation to these two factors.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what is the... what is the message you want to convey to the mind regarding ill-will?
[SPEAKER_03]: So that it drops it, so it doesn't want it, so it stops going towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we talked about satirity and everything else, but how about ill-will?
[SPEAKER_03]: You know it's bad, you know it's harmful, but the animal still leans towards it every now and then, when it's annoyed.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you teach it not to?
[SPEAKER_03]: Remember, we spoke about the reward.
[SPEAKER_03]: When the animal does the right thing, on account of you showing it, I want to reward it, so it starts doing it by itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same with the dog training.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't want to always have to guide it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want it to do it on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how I learned.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, your behavior is the guidance, but it's still not doing on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is the message you want to convey, so it starts doing on its own?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it starts to prefer it.
[SPEAKER_03]: To prefer the non-anger over anger.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the message in relation to anger specifically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you want to be happy in life?
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're angry, are you happy?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes?
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's the question you should be asking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: The sole reason for the anger is to get back onto the happiness, to get back onto the satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when it gets angry, when it gets disturbed, it doesn't know that it doesn't have to go through the motions of expressing anger and acting out to get where it wants to be from the start.
[SPEAKER_03]: All it needs to do is, oh, I don't want to...
[SPEAKER_03]: I won't be angry, and it's back where you want it to be from the start.
[SPEAKER_02]: The verse from the Dhammapada, aversion cannot be dispelled by aversion, it can only be dispelled by non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yeah, that's basically in heart of every anger or irritation.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's that pressure from the animal, because it doesn't know that actually, there and then, it has the option to be free from it instantly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why anger is quickly dispelled, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_03]: Blameworthy,
[SPEAKER_03]: But quickly dispelled.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same as sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're dropping the wanting of this thing, because you don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where's the pressure there?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dropping the not-wanting of this pressure, it's irritating pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're no pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no resistance to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's no resistance to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just with anger, you get almost
[SPEAKER_03]: Instantly verified effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: With sensuality, you don't.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why sensuality is not blameworthy, but a lot harder to give up.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what they describe.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in a sense of, like, say somebody makes you angry, somebody insults you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, they don't make you angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: They insult you.
[SPEAKER_03]: They do something to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You get angry on account of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, somebody disrespects you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now you have all these options of how you would deal with that.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would obviously require that person, or even more people, and so on, and it's this and that to address, it never happens again, so it's corrected, so they know their mistake, all of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But obviously, that would be exactly on the level of, okay, so the anger, you believe the anger came from over there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's how you're going to treat this condition, by talking about it, and sharing your feelings, and making everything known, how you feel inside, to everybody.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that will work only for how long?
[SPEAKER_03]: Till somebody forgets.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or until you are in a bad mood and then start interpreting everything as disrespect, because of your own insecurity.
[SPEAKER_03]: But instead, say somebody intentionally disrespects you.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not even accidental.
[SPEAKER_03]: And as I said, you have an option to take on now that burden of dealing with this, or to say, okay, I do not have to deal with this person ever again for the rest of my life.
[SPEAKER_03]: And isn't that a wonderful feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, completely elevated.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any burden, any sense, no hatred, no love either.
[SPEAKER_03]: But certainly, there is no reason for hatred, because there is nothing I'm trying to express or deal with.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, you're not my problem anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, I like you for that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I have no sense of duty towards you, because you didn't earn it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the same when the Buddha went to the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Gift.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the gift, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, I meant the Kosambi, when they were quarreling.
[SPEAKER_03]: When he said, stop quarreling, it's, you know, you're incurring a lot of demerit.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he says, well, mind your own business, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's our demerit, not your demerit.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he told them three times, and three times they dismissed him.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's like, okay, this foolish man, and he went off.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you think, like, oh, so he was completely disrespected.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, not my problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, when Sariputta and Mahatma Gandhi came back and started, come on, let's let's go back and help them, he did.
[SPEAKER_03]: He wasn't angry with them.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, well, now I won't go, because they offended me.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, they said, oh, you know, they were obviously lost perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's for their welfare.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, let's do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: But either way, basically, by people, people, by disrespect, by
[SPEAKER_03]: Any, any kind of abuse directed at you, that in itself automatically reminds you how free you are from them.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the gift-suitor.
[SPEAKER_03]: When he's throwing insults at him and says, oh, let me give you an example.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you give gifts and they don't accept it, who did... like, I can't accept it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I don't know, I can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm unable to accept what you're giving me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Who does that stay with?
[SPEAKER_03]: With you.
[SPEAKER_03]: That entire experience stays with you, does not become my problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: All because citta has been taught to recognize that very thing which didn't recognize before, which is why the whole pressure and then you couldn't stop thinking about it and winding yourself up more and more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: No one can make you angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: No one can make you angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: And people trying to make you angry would then make you even less angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: More unangry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because nobody ever could make you angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's a pressure towards anger, you realize, okay, not expressing it, not giving into it, not acting out of it, and then conveying the message to the chitta that, actually, just try it, just, just, you know, humor me for a second, drop it, and you'll see that's what you wanted from the start, when you wanted to go through the anger, every time you did in the past.
[SPEAKER_03]: And actually, it's the same for sensuality as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: The outcome of it is what you want and you can actually have more direct access to it by dropping sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's that the monk who said to the deva, when he said like, oh, why are you forsaking what's visible here and now for some uncertain goal later?
[SPEAKER_03]: He's like, no, what you're talking about?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: I am practicing what's accessible here and now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead,
[SPEAKER_03]: of the uncertain results later, which is sensuality, is always uncertain, implies the time, implies the sequence, implies the uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_03]: Giving it up immediately, then and then, gives you the satisfaction you wanted through it.